Guide to the Charles Melville Pepper collection, 1800-1945 MS2377
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Charles Melville Pepper papers
1800-1945
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Charles Melville Pepper, 1859-1930
MS2377
6.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains correspondence, publications, photographs, genealogical documents and miscellaneous souvenirs from the collection of Charles Melville Pepper. The bulk of the material pertains to his travels and research in Latin America. The material dates between 1800-1945.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Paper records and Books.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Wall, March 7, 2017 (2017.006)
Biographical / Historical
Charles Melville Pepper (1859-1930) was a writer who focused his work on Latin America. Pepper was born in Morrow County, Ohio on November 11, 1859. In 1881, Pepper graduated from Wooster College in Ohio. Pepper married Kitty Rose on May 4, 1884. They had one daughter.
Charles Melville Pepper was a newspaper correspondent, commissioner for the Pan-American Railway, commissioner for the Department of Commerce and and advisor to the Department of State. He spent most of his life traveling. Pepper was a staff correspondent for the New York Herald in 1896, reporting on the election. After the election, Pepper covered President McKinley's activities. Soon after this, Pepper went to Cuba to write for several newspapers about the insurrection and the following American occupation.
In 1901, President McKinley appointed Pepper to be one of the five delegates to the Second Pan-American Conference. In 1903, President Roosevelt made pepper the Pan-American Railway Commissioner.
In addition to his work on Latin America, Pepper was also made a special trade commissioner for the Department of Commerce in 1906 and later a foreign-trade advisor to the Department of State in 1909. During these year he negotiated the Canadian reciprocity agreement under President Taft. In 1913 he resigned from these positions and spent many years as a news correspondent in Central and South America. In 1918, after becoming a representative of American firms engaged in Chilean trade, Pepper became the director of the Chile-American Association.
Pepper published many books in addition to his news articles and government reports including: To-Morrow in Cuba, Everyday Life in Washington and Panama to Patagonia.
Pepper died on November 4, 1930 in New York, NY at the age of 70.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, publications, photographs, genealogical documents, and miscellaneous souvenirs. The material dates between 1800-1945. These are the records of Charles Melville Pepper from throughout his life, including many documents from his wife Kitty Rose Pepper. In 1901, Pepper was asked to serve on the Pan-American Congress. The bulk of this collection relates to Pepper's travels in Latin America.
Patagonia (Argentina and Chile); Latin America - Description and Travel; Journalism; United States -- District of Columbia -- Washington; United States--Politics and government; International American Conference (2nd: 1901-1902: Mexico City, Mexico)
- Paper records, Series 1
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically by folder title.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, publications, photographs, genealogical documents, and miscellaneous souvenirs. The material dates between 1800-1945. These are the records of Charles Melville Pepper from throughout his life, including many documents from his wife Kitty Rose Pepper. In 1901, Pepper was asked to serve on the Pan-American Congress. The bulk of this collection relates to Pepper's travels in Latin America.
  - The Book of C.M.P., 1897-1907; MS2377 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Book of C.M.P. II, 1907-1914; MS2377 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Book of C.M.P. Vol. 3, 1914-1926; MS2377 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Canadian Reciprocal Trade Treaty [1/2], 1910; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Canadian Reciprocal Trade Treaty [2/2], 1910; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter Revisions for Marcy Book, Undated; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charles M. Pepper Twenty Five Years, 1922; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chile American/Panama Canal/Grace Line, 1903-1933; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chile Notebook, 1933; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chile Notes, 1903-1908; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspndence/Canadian Reciprocity, 1911; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence/Memos About Canada, 1910-1913; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Death of Kitty Rose Pepper, 1911; MS2377 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Department of State Documents, 1910; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Evening Public Ledger, 1918; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Filibusters, 1854-1922; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Kitty Rose Pepper Correspondence and Photographs, 1887-1926; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [Kittie] Rose Pepper Vol. 1, 1873-1902; MS2377 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts and Book Drafts, Undated; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mexican Album, 1901-1902; MS2377 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Including Diploma, Government Documents etc., 1875-1930; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Papers/Photographs, 1885-1920; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings Scrapbook, 1915-1917; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Scrapbook - Articles about and by Charles Melville Pepper, 1897-1917; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Scrapbook by Charles Melville Pepper, 1896-1929; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pan American Papers, 1890-1912; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Pepper Family File", 1930-1933; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1904-1926; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photo Album, 1904; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photo Album, 1905; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report Cards and Address to the Democratic National Convention, 1888; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rose Pepper Correspondence, 1800-1930; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rose Pepper Miscellaneous, 1841-1905; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1896-1906; MS2377 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of Articles about FDR, 1940-1945; MS2377 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks - "Letters", 1907-1911; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook - News Articles, 1885-1896; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook - News Articles, 1882-1890; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kitty Rose Pepper Scrapbook, 1898; MS2377 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook of Articles, Undated; MS2377 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook of Articles, 1921-1925; MS2377 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook of Articles, 1918; MS2377 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - CMP Scrapbook, 1925-1929; MS2377 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Small Notebooks, 1903-1930; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - South American Trade, 1911; MS2377 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - William Marcy Papers, 1845-1849; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - William Marcy Book Rejections/Documents, 1854-1929; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - William Marcy Book Draft, 1929; MS2377 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The World War Vol. 2, 1915-1917; MS2377 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The World War Vol. 1, 1914-1915; MS2377 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Books, 1905-1930; Series 2
  This series is composed of books by Charles Melville Pepper including:
  South American Trade 1907-1908, Charles Melville Pepper, 1907-1908
  European Reports 1908-1910, Charles Melville Pepper, 1908-1909
  The West in the Orient, Charles Melville Pepper, 1908
  Congressional Directory 1st Session 57th Congress (newspaper articles pasted inside), Unknown numerous
  Congressional Directory 2nd Session 53th Congress, Charles Melville Pepper, Pasted over dates
  Pan American Papers 1899-1909, Charles Melville Pepper, 1899-1909
  Report on the Trade Conditions in Canada, Charles Melville Pepper, 1906
  Pan American Railway, Charles Melville Pepper, 1904
  Trade Conditions, Charles Melville Pepper, 1905-1906
  Trade Conditions, Charles Melville Pepper, 1906-1907
  Guatemala, Charles Melville Pepper, 1906
  Chile American Association Monographs II, Charles Melville Pepper, 1926-1930
  Chile American Association Monographs, Charles Melville Pepper, 1921-1924
  Arranged in no particular order.
  - Books authored by Charles Melville Pepper, Series 2 (Box 8)
  - Books authored by Charles Melville Pepper, Series 2 (Box 9)